Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we feature a
wide variety of research
and we start with a study
that reveals an effective way
to help people reduce
their meat consumption.
According to a survey of more
than 30,000 U.S. residents,
a third of American adults
self-identify as meat reducers,
meaning one in three of us is trying
to cut down on our meat consumption.
Why?
For those earning less than
$40,000 a year, the #1 reason is cost;
for those earning more than $40K,
the #1 reason is health.
And indeed, if we were
to define a healthy diet,
compared to how we're eating now,
we should be eating more
plant-based foods,
including fresh fruits and vegetables,
whole grains, legumes --
meaning beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils -- seeds and nuts,
and at the same time
lower in animal foods,
particularly fatty and
processed meats.
In an editorial entitled
"Plant-Based Diets for Personal,
Population, and Planetary Health,"
co-authored by the chair
of nutrition at Harvard,
healthy plant-based diets are
not only more sustainable,
but have also been associated
with lower risk of chronic diseases
such as obesity, type 2 diabetes,
cardiovascular disease,
and some cancers.
What do we mean by plant-based?
Basically, any diet that reduces
the amount of animal products
and increases the amount of plants --
again, vegetables, fruits, whole grains,
legumes, nuts, and seeds.
Transitioning global diets towards
healthy plant-based dietary patterns
would require large-scale
public health efforts
but could be instrumental in ensuring
future human and planetary health.
Indeed, the IPCC, the Intergovernmental
Panel on Climate Change,
describes plant-based diets as
a major opportunity for mitigating
and adapting
to climate change
and includes a policy recommendation
to reduce meat consumption.
Okay, but how do you do it?
In a systematic review of
experimental studies on strategies
to reduce meat consumption,
one of the most effective experiments
came out of the Midwest.
Sadly, research shows that the
provision of information on its own
can be of limited utility in
facilitating behavioral change.
However, default interventions have
been successfully employed
in a variety of prosocial contexts,
making the right option or
the healthiest option,
the easiest option --
the default option.
Take for example,
organ donation.
Every year, thousands
of people in the United States
have died waiting for
a suitable donor organ.
But wait -- 85% of Americans
approve of organ donation,
yet less than half have made
a decision about donating, and
fewer still have granted permission
by signing a donor card.
If you look at Europe, there's
nearly a ten-fold difference
in the organ donor rates
across different countries.
In some countries, consent
is only about 10%,
while in others
it's up to like 99.9%.
What's the difference
between the two colors?
Gold is opt-in;
blue is opt-out.
In opt-out countries, the default
is that people are organ donors
unless they actively
register not to be.
In the opt-in countries
like the United States,
the default is nobody
is an organ donor
without explicitly registering
to be one.
So there's all sorts of calls for
campaigns to change public attitudes
about organ donation, but remember
85% are already on board.
If we want to change behavior
and not just attitudes,
changing the default condition
may be more effective.
So does it work for diet?
In the DEFAULT treatment,
participants received at their table
a menu listing only
five meat-free options.
But they were informed -- verbally
and in writing on the menu --
that they could also consult a second
menu that was posted on the wall
about a dozen feet away,
which had your standard array
of popular nonvegetarian
dining hall dishes.
And in the control condition
both lists of options
were mixed together on the
same menu they were handed.
And when you do that,
only a minority of people
choose the meat-free options,
between 5 and 40%,
depending on if you describe
the meat-free options
in an appealing way, like
pasta with Provencal vegetables,
or in unappealing terms
like vegan calzone.
Okay, but what about
the default condition,
where the menu in front
of them is all meat-free.
They can still get up and order
all the meat they want,
but the alternate menu
is a few steps away.
You're not taking away
any people's options,
but just by making it the default,
meat-free choices shot up
like to 75 and 90%.
Even an unappealingly described
meat-free option totally won out.
And even just adding more veg
options, from a quarter of the options
to half the options,
may increase the sales
of the veg options
between about 40 to 80%.
In our next story,
I share a touching story of the
power of plant-based eating
for chronic kidney failure.
Is it possible to ameliorate
chronic kidney disease
using a whole food,
plant-based diet?
In my last video
on kidney disease,
I talked about how randomizing
people to cut just around
10 grams of protein from their
daily diet could cut their risk
of dialysis and death
by a whopping 77%.
That was cutting protein
across the board.
But while animal-based
protein ingestion —
meat, dairy, and egg white
promotes an acidic environment
in the kidneys, inflammation, and
stresses the kidneys to what's
called hyperfiltration mode,
plant-based protein can be
alkaline-producing and
anti-inflammatory and contain
kidney-protective properties.
So, what if you have kidney patients
eat a plant-dominant low-protein diet,
abbreviated adorably as PLADO,
I guess for plant-dominant.
If you fashion up a plant-based diet
index score where you get points
for healthy plant foods
and get points deducted
for eating animal foods,
those with serious kidney disease
with higher scores were found
to have lower systemic inflammation.
But does that actually translate
into living a longer life?
Apparently so.
Even a 10% increase in the
proportion of plant-based protein
was associated with a significant
reduction in all-cause mortality.
Even just eating more servings of
fruits and vegetables, like two a day
compared to two a week,
is linked to living longer.
Without fully functioning kidneys,
there are concerns about
phosphorus and potassium overload,
though, on a plant-based diet.
But the phosphorus in plant-based
foods is not as much of a problem
as the phosphorus additives
in processed and animal foods.
And the risk of potassium overload
from plant-based diets appears
overstated and not supported
by the evidence.
But you don't know about
ameliorating chronic kidney disease
using a whole food, plant-based
diet until you put it to the test.
Here's a case report of a 69-year-old
man with type 2 diabetes,
high blood pressure, and
stage 3 chronic kidney disease,
resulting in elevated phosphorus
and potassium in the blood,
Interested in changing his diet
to improve his medical condition.
That's my kind of patient!
He was on 12 different medications,
eating a diet that may actually be
slightly better than
the average American:
some whole grains and beans,
but then his doctor advised to try
eating whole food, plant-based.
So, oatmeal with fruit and flax,
beans and greens,
whole wheat spaghetti and
veggies, fruit as snacks.
Counselled to eat as much as he
wanted from whole healthy foods;
no carb counting, no calorie counting,
no portion size restriction —
improving the quality of food rather
than restricting the quantity of food.
He adopted the whole food,
plant-based diet, packed with carbs,
yet rapidly reduced his insulin
requirements by more than 50%,
and subsequently saw
improvements in weight,
blood pressure,
and cholesterol.
Because eating healthy
can have such a rapid effect
on improving your body's
insulin sensitivity,
immediate adjustments
in insulin dosing were made.
Within four days, his insulin dose
was able to be reduced
from roughly 210 units of insulin
a day down to 70 units daily,
and an oral blood-sugar lowering
medication had to be stopped
due to rapidly improving blood sugar.
He also was able to stop his
carvedilol, the hydrochlorothiazide,
amlodipine, sitagliptin
within the first two months
due to improving blood pressure
and blood sugars.
His insulin dose was
steadily titrated downward.
His pravastatin dose was cut in half,
and he lost about 50 pounds.
Okay, so what happened
to his stage 3 kidney failure?
He was no longer in
stage 3 kidney failure!
Doctors watching this will understand
what all these numbers mean.
Here's a graph of his GFR, which
is a measure of kidney function,
declining for years before shooting
up after he started eating healthy.
He experienced an increase
in estimated GFR of 73%,
suggesting that the improvement
in estimated kidney function
was greater than what would be
expected from weight loss alone.
For example, lose about 60 pounds
from bariatric surgery,
and you only get
about a 12 to 15% boost.
Bottom line: for individuals
with chronic kidney disease,
especially those with obesity,
hypertension, or diabetes,
a strict, all-you-care-to-eat
whole food, plant-based diet
may confer significant benefit.
I mean, apart from the
kidney-specific outcomes,
overall mortality is significantly
lower among kidney patients
who eat more plants.
And that's critical because most
kidney patients don't even make it
to dialysis because they die first,
most often from
cardiovascular disease.
Let's hear from the patient.
"At the outset, it seemed like
this was going to be a difficult
and restrictive way to eat,
but I began feeling different
almost immediately
and we had to decrease
my insulin after ONE day.
It seemed like almost overnight I had
more energy than I'd had in years.
Weight I'd been trying to lose for
a decade began dropping off.
As the weight came off, I felt lighter,
and more able to move my body again.
This lifestyle change has been
the greatest gift I've ever received.
I am off most of my medications,
I've lost over 70 pounds,
and I've regained control
over my health.
I feel empowered
by this lifestyle change,
and I finally feel like I'm
in charge of my health,
not just an unlucky victim shuffling
from one specialist to the next.
My only regret was that
I didn't know about this sooner."
Finally today,
we look at how stress
and menstrual cycles
can affect the smell of our breath.
According to the American
Dental Association,
about 50% of American adults
suffer from oral malodor,
with prevalence rates around the world
ranging from 2% to nearly 80%.
On average, it seems to be about
one in three of us on the planet Earth
have bad breath.
What effect might
stress have on the smell of our breath?
Stressed students were found
to have significantly higher levels
of the "rotten egg" gas,
hydrogen sulfide,
which is one of the main volatile sulfur
compounds related to bad breath,
originating from the degradation of the
sulfur-containing amino acid cysteine,
found concentrated in animal
proteins like meat and dairy.
Were they eating different diets
or just too busy to brush?
The simplest explanation
is just the dry mouth you get
when you're super-stressed,
part of our fight or flight response.
It's the same reason
we get morning breath,
because we have decreased
saliva production when we sleep
that would otherwise
self-clean the mouth,
keeping it from becoming
like a stagnant pond.
Though maybe stress hormones
are having an effect as well.
We suspect sex hormones may play
a role, since though men and women
have the same before-and-after
rise in bad breath compounds
after a stressful situation,
women seem to start out
with higher baseline levels.
Gender appears to play
an important role.
Women have significantly worse
morning breath, for example,
and bad breath is affected
by the menstrual cycle.
In fact, that's listed as one of the
causes: so-called menstrual breath.
As you can see, there are higher
levels of bad breath compounds
in the mouths of women in the
premenstrual and menstrual phases
compared not just to men,
but the follicular phase
of their own cycle,
meaning like the first half
before ovulation.
Hmm, so maybe bad breath is a hormonal
thing more than just a dry mouth thing.
But salivary flow is also lower in
menstrual and premenstrual phases.
Check it out: significantly
less salivary flow
during menstrual flow
and right before.
So, is this all just about having
a drier mouth during stress
and certain times of the month?
How could you tease out the effects?
Well, what about studying
stressful periods.
PMS, premenstrual syndrome,
is a stressful state characterized
by irritability, tension, mood swings.
Is the menstrual dry mouth and
bad breath just due to period stress?
Apparently so.
If you split women up
into those who experience PMS and
those who don't, it's only those
with PMS who suffer the rise
in bad breath compounds
as their period arrives.
But the salivary flow was
not statistically different.
So the results suggest that
a stressful situation can be
a predisposing factor for bad breath
that may have nothing to do
with dry mouth or salivary flow.
So what's going on?
It's the effects of the stress
hormones themselves
on the production of
bad breath compounds.
They dripped some stress
hormones on bad breath bacteria---
hormones like adrenaline
and cortisol---
and they started churning out
more hydrogen sulfide.
What can we do about it
if we can't treat the cause
and reduce the stress?
I have videos on dietary
changes that can help
as well as tongue cleaning methods.
And I have videos in the works
on the effects of gum chewing
and the best mouthwash to use
that doesn't kill the good
bacteria in your mouth.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.